So we have seen that our predict not
taken predictor that is very simple to
implement is pretty accurate for about
88% of all instructions. It predicts
correctly. So why do we even need any
better predictors because anything
better than this will require some
investment of hardware to do the
prediction better. We will answer this
question in two ways. First we will
compare the CPI with the not taken
predictor that is let's say 88% accurate
and with a better predictor that is
let's say 99% accurate. And we will do
this for a five- stage pipeline that
resolves branches in the third stage. So
it has a two cycle penalty whenever
there is a misprediction. So it has a
two cycle penalty when there is a
misprediction.
We will also do it for a 14 stage
pipeline that resolves branches in the
11th stage. So it has a 10 cycle penalty
for a
misprediction. And for another pipeline
that has 14 stages, resolves branches in
11th stage. But this one executes four
instructions per cycle. So this is very
close to what modern processors look
like. So for a not taken predictor and a
five-stage pipe, the CPI we get is 1
plus how often we mispredict which is
12% of all instructions times the
penalty of a misprediction which is two
cycles which gives us a total CPI of
1.24. What happens when we have a better
predictor? Well, we now get 1 + 0.01 01
only 1% of the time we mispredict and we
get a two cycle penalty then so the CPI
now is
102 and now let's look also at the speed
up that we get from a better predictor
if the frequency of the processor stays
the same and it executes the same number
of instructions then the speed up is
simply the improvement in the CPI so the
speed up would be the CPI of the not
taken predict but divided by the CPI of
the better predictor and we get a speed
up of
1.22. This is actually a noticeable
speed up. But things get more
interesting when we have a deeper
pipeline. In that case, we have 1 +
still 12% accuracy for not taken. But
this time, the penalty because we
resolve branches in 11th stage will be
10 and we get an overall CPI of 2.2.
two. This is much worse than the one we
would be getting with no
mispredictions. With our better
predictor, we get 1 + 1% misprediction
rate time 10 for a total CPI of
1.1 and that gives us a speed up of two.
So as we can see now the better
predictor is giving us twice the
performance of the not taken predictor.
And we have seen this already that the
deeper the pipeline the more benefit we
get from a better predictor. But what
happens when we also do multiple
instructions per cycle. So this
processor can do four instructions in a
cycle. So the ideal cycles per
instruction is one quarter of a cycle.
We add to that how often we have
mispredictions times how many cycles do
we waste for a misprediction. we still
detect mispredictions in the 11th stage.
So everything done in the 10 cycles
after the branch was fetched is wasted.
So we still have a 10 cycle penalty here
and we get an overall CPI of
1.45. That's actually less than one
instruction per cycle. It's better than
a single instruction per cycle
processor, but not that much better for
something that should be four times as
capable. Now, let's look at the better
predictor, which should give us the
ideal CPI plus 1% of the time 10 cycle
penalty. And that results in a CPI of
0.35 or about three instructions per
cycle even with the branches. If we
compute the speed up, it's 4.14.
So as you can see if we have a deeper
pipeline or if we are able to execute
more instructions per cycle then the
better predictor is more important than
in simpler processors.